<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: howto | Hron's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://hron.me/blog/tags/howto/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hron.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-28T02:10:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hron.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gábor Garami]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New scanner added successfully]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/07/new-scanner-added-successfully/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T01:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/07/new-scanner-added-successfully</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had to buy a new printer because my old Xerox Phaser stopped working and I got
a horrible price for repairing it. After browsing the possible applicants, I found
the Philips LaserMFD 6050 what have an automatic document feeder addon too.
After unpacking it, I was happy because I found a driver CD with title "Mac &amp; Linux"
But I didn't know the afternoon-long sucking will start.</p>

<p>At first place I want to make printer part working. After printing one of printer's
own test pages, I sat down behind my Gentoo box, and started figure out how can
I introduce my new printer to Cups. The first step was easy, because it found a
new printer-like device at USB port, but it had absolute no idea about the type.</p>

<p>After a lot of googling, i found it's a dumb printer without PCL or PS knowledge,
so I had to install 'raster' driver. The funny part is all Linux driver was 32 bit.</p>

<p>Fortunately, cups invokes parts of the driver via command-line (not via shared
libraries like sane - see later), so I have very little debugging task with it.
Ohh, and I have to patch it because Gentoo uses /usr/libexec for cups drivers,
not /usr/lib what assumed by <code>rastertoprinter</code> script.</p>

<p>However, sometimes cups does not print the job at first try, I have to reprint it
from the web interface - I didn't guessed it why. This is a very small issue, so
I marked this task completed.</p>

<p>Scanner part was more tricky. As I said, all drivers on the CD (and in the
driver package what I downloaded from the internet) was for 32bit not for 64 bit
systems. Sane's backends are dynamic libraries, so there was no quick and
painless way to add proprietary backend to my existing Sane install. As i browsed
hopeless on the internet, I found a topic what said the drivers on the CD are for
Ubuntu Gutsy (and works with Hardy too). This gave me an idea: what happens if I
install a 32bit Ubuntu Hardy chroot?</p>

<p>To understand my idea you have to know Sane has a small inetd/xinetd daemon named
<code>saned</code> and it can provide your scanner on the network. So you can connect from
any (permitted) client to your server and scan even if your box is not connected
to the scanner directly (e.g. via USB cable).</p>

<p>After emerging <code>debootstrap</code>, I installed Hardy into a simple /chroot32 folder,
and added sane stuffs for it. I unpacked the provided sane backend into this
chroot and sane finally recognized my scanner correctly. After some testing I
configured saned with this xinetd config:</p>

<p>```plain /etc/xinetd.d/sane-port
service sane-port
{</p>

<pre><code>disable     = no
socket_type = stream
protocol    = tcp
user        = root
group       = root
wait        = no
server      = /usr/sbin/saned
only_from   = 127.0.0.1 ::1 192.168.2.0/24
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>I had to run saned as root because saned got permission denied otherwise. As
it's running in chroot and restricted to the local network, it has a very low
risk.</p>

<p>Finally I can scan via XSane. Gimp is not allow me to scan from this device, but
XSane is smart enough for me.</p>

<p>For bulk scanning i wrote a small bash script. It needs some love because it
creates a pdf in the current working directory - but it's good for start.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/6096805.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
