<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: en | Hron's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://hron.me/blog/tags/en/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hron.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-28T02:10:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hron.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[G치bor Garami]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New scanner added successfully]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/07/new-scanner-added-successfully/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-28T01:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/07/new-scanner-added-successfully</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had to buy a new printer because my old Xerox Phaser stopped working and I got
a horrible price for repairing it. After browsing the possible applicants, I found
the Philips LaserMFD 6050 what have an automatic document feeder addon too.
After unpacking it, I was happy because I found a driver CD with title "Mac &amp; Linux"
But I didn't know the afternoon-long sucking will start.</p>

<p>At first place I want to make printer part working. After printing one of printer's
own test pages, I sat down behind my Gentoo box, and started figure out how can
I introduce my new printer to Cups. The first step was easy, because it found a
new printer-like device at USB port, but it had absolute no idea about the type.</p>

<p>After a lot of googling, i found it's a dumb printer without PCL or PS knowledge,
so I had to install 'raster' driver. The funny part is all Linux driver was 32 bit.</p>

<p>Fortunately, cups invokes parts of the driver via command-line (not via shared
libraries like sane - see later), so I have very little debugging task with it.
Ohh, and I have to patch it because Gentoo uses /usr/libexec for cups drivers,
not /usr/lib what assumed by <code>rastertoprinter</code> script.</p>

<p>However, sometimes cups does not print the job at first try, I have to reprint it
from the web interface - I didn't guessed it why. This is a very small issue, so
I marked this task completed.</p>

<p>Scanner part was more tricky. As I said, all drivers on the CD (and in the
driver package what I downloaded from the internet) was for 32bit not for 64 bit
systems. Sane's backends are dynamic libraries, so there was no quick and
painless way to add proprietary backend to my existing Sane install. As i browsed
hopeless on the internet, I found a topic what said the drivers on the CD are for
Ubuntu Gutsy (and works with Hardy too). This gave me an idea: what happens if I
install a 32bit Ubuntu Hardy chroot?</p>

<p>To understand my idea you have to know Sane has a small inetd/xinetd daemon named
<code>saned</code> and it can provide your scanner on the network. So you can connect from
any (permitted) client to your server and scan even if your box is not connected
to the scanner directly (e.g. via USB cable).</p>

<p>After emerging <code>debootstrap</code>, I installed Hardy into a simple /chroot32 folder,
and added sane stuffs for it. I unpacked the provided sane backend into this
chroot and sane finally recognized my scanner correctly. After some testing I
configured saned with this xinetd config:</p>

<p>```plain /etc/xinetd.d/sane-port
service sane-port
{</p>

<pre><code>disable     = no
socket_type = stream
protocol    = tcp
user        = root
group       = root
wait        = no
server      = /usr/sbin/saned
only_from   = 127.0.0.1 ::1 192.168.2.0/24
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>I had to run saned as root because saned got permission denied otherwise. As
it's running in chroot and restricted to the local network, it has a very low
risk.</p>

<p>Finally I can scan via XSane. Gimp is not allow me to scan from this device, but
XSane is smart enough for me.</p>

<p>For bulk scanning i wrote a small bash script. It needs some love because it
creates a pdf in the current working directory - but it's good for start.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/6096805.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code></code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rename Windows 8 Profile dir]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/04/rename-windows-8-profile-dir/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T00:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/04/rename-windows-8-profile-dir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I ran into a weird situation: when I installed Windows, I used Live account to create my user.
In preview version of Windows 8 it created a profile dir based on the user part of e-mail address
of the Live account, so from hrgy@live.com it created an user hrgy with same profile dir. However,
the final version is changed it to create account based on your first name, it was "G치bor" in this
case. Notice the accented second letter.</p>

<p>The problem with folders containing non-ASCII char in its name is obvious: not all program can handle
it correctly. It has a displaying problems in some apps, and some apps cannot create their files in
this profile.</p>

<p>The fix was not so easy but I now describe required steps.</p>

<p>First if you do not have an another administrator user than you, then you have to create it. Windows 8
does not allow to log into the built-in Administrator account anymore, so you have to create one in
Control Panel. It's pretty straighforward and net contains a bunch of howtos for it, so I skip describing
this step.</p>

<p>Now, log out from your account, and log in into the new one.</p>

<p>Start <code>regedit</code> and navigate to <code>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows NT\CurrentVersion\ProfileList</code></p>

<p>In the subkeys (subfolders) find one what displays your old dirname in <code>ProfileImagePath</code> attribute. In my
case the value was <code>C:\Users\G치bor</code>. Right click, edit and replace last part of the path to what you want to use.</p>

<p><strong>Important:</strong> Even if world collapsing, <strong>do not log in into your own account (what being modified)</strong>
until you finish these steps!</p>

<p>Then, you have to reboot into Safe mode. The easiest way is press <code>Shift + F8</code> during boot. If you
seeing the Windows splash displaying in "wrong" resolution then you are in Safe mode.</p>

<p><strong>Important:</strong> you have to log in into the newly created admin account, <em>not</em> into your own one!</p>

<p>Then you have to rename your profile folder. Start a command prompt in Safe mode, and type following:</p>

<pre><code>cd C:\Users
move old_name new_name
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>old_name</code> is the old name of your profile directory, the <code>new_name</code> is what you specified in RegEdit. In
my case it was:</p>

<pre><code>cd C:\Users
move G치bor hron
</code></pre>

<p>Now you are done! If you striclty follwed this tutorial, then if you reboot and log in into your account, you do not see
any change, except the %USERPROFILE% environment variable carries the new name.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> I saw only one bug: iCloud Photo stream stored the full path of my Pictures folder in its database and I had to relocate it.
It's a bug in iCloud, not a Windows problem.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: This tutorial is tested by me but I do not guarantee anything. Take a backup from your important data before start doing
this. I am not responsible if your data lose, you cannot login anymore or your kitten vanishes.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails pre-commit hook]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/02/rails-pre-commit-hook/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T23:23:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/02/rails-pre-commit-hook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just created this small hook for my Rails projects. It helps me to make my codebase clean.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/4774014.js?file=git-pre-commit-hook.rb'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/usr/bin/env ruby

require 'erb'
require 'yaml'
require 'pp'

lines = %x{git diff-index --cached --name-only HEAD}.split(/[\r\n]+/)

ENV['RAILS_ENV'] = 'test'

lines.each do |file|
  if File.exists?(file) and file =~ /\.(rb|rake|god)$/
    print &quot;[SYNTAX] #{file} - &quot;
    ret = system(&quot;ruby -c '#{file}'&quot;)
    exit 1 unless ret

    if file =~ /_test\.rb$/
      print &quot;[UNIT  ] #{file} - &quot;
      unitcmd = &quot;ruby -Ilib:test #{file}&quot;
      unitcmd = &quot;bundle exec #{unitcmd}&quot; if File.exists?('Gemfile')
      ret = system(unitcmd)
      exit 1 unless ret
    end

    if file =~ /_spec\.rb$/
      print &quot;[SPEC  ] #{file} - &quot;
      rspeccmd = &quot;rspec #{file}&quot;
      rspeccmd = &quot;bundle exec #{rspeccmd}&quot; if File.exists?('Gemfile')
      ret = system(rspeccmd)
      exit 1 unless ret
    end
  end

  if File.exists?(file) and File.basename(file) =~ /^(Capfile|Gemfile|Guardfile|Rakefile|config.ru)$/
    print &quot;[SYNTAX] #{file} - &quot;
    ret = system(&quot;ruby -c '#{file}'&quot;)
    exit 1 unless ret
  end

  if File.exists?(file) and file =~ /\.feature$/
    print &quot;[ (::) ] #{file} - &quot;
    ENV['CUCUMBER_FORMAT'] = 'progress'
    cuccmd = &quot;cucumber #{file}&quot;
    cuccmd = &quot;bundle exec #{cuccmd}&quot; if File.exists?('Gemfile')
    ret = system(cuccmd)
    exit 1 unless ret
  end

  if File.exists?(file) and file =~ /\.(yml|yaml)$/
    print &quot;[SYNTAX] #{file} - &quot;
    begin
      # Load with erb to avoid problems with cucumber's yml
      erb = ERB.new(IO.read(file)).result(binding)
      yaml = YAML.load(erb)
      puts &quot;Syntax OK&quot;
    rescue SyntaxError =&gt; ex
      puts ex.message
      exit 1
    rescue ArgumentError =&gt; ex
      puts ex.message
      exit 1
    end
  end
end
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>You can clone it at <a href="https://gist.github.com/hron84/4774014">Gist</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gitiles Install Howto]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/01/gitiles-install-howto/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T17:12:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/01/gitiles-install-howto</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I sucked a bit with <a href="https://code.google.com/p/gitiles/">Gitiles</a>, Gerrit's Gitweb implementation, because this project lacks an INSTALL file.</p>

<p>So, basically you have to do following:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>First, check out of the source:</p>

<p> <code>git clone https://gerrit.googlesource.com/gitiles</code></p></li>
<li><p>After you cloned the source, compile it with <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a>:</p>

<p> <code>mvn package -Dmaven.test.skip=true</code></p></li>
</ul>


<p>  Now, you got <strong>gitiles-war-1.0-SNAPSHOT.war</strong> in gitiles-war/target folder. Deploy it under your application server, in this case I put it to Jetty's webapps folder.</p>

<ul>
<li>Tricky part is coming: you will faced with an error message, what says some configuration options are missing. This is because you didn't created any configuration file yet. By default, webapp searches its configuration in the webapp root folder, but - because jetty explodes this folder every restart, I decided to put it to some more persistent place. I am do not run any other thing under this Jetty than Gerrit and Gitiles, so I created the gitiles.config under Jetty's etc folder:</li>
</ul>


<p>```text gitiles.config
[gitiles]</p>

<pre><code># Repositories placed here
basePath = /srv/git/repositories
# Do not check they are exported
exportAll = true
# This URL will be displayed as clone URL. DO NOT FORGET TRAILING SLASH!
baseGitUrl = ssh://cr.hron.me:29418/
# Title of site (doh)
siteTitle  = Gitiles - kingmax.hron.me:/srv/git/repositories
# I dunno why, but it is have to be configured.
canonicalHostName = kingmax.hron.me
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<ul>
<li>The config file above is cool, but Gitiles still crying... yeah, because you have to tell where it should find that. To do this, you must export a System property <strong>com.google.gitiles.configPath</strong>. I was <em>very</em> lazy, so I edited jetty.xml and before last closing tag I pasted this:</li>
</ul>


<p>```xml jetty.xml</p>

<pre><code>&lt;Call class="java.lang.System" name="setProperty"&gt;
    &lt;Arg&gt;com.google.gitiles.configPath&lt;/Arg&gt;
    &lt;Arg&gt;&lt;SystemProperty name="jetty.home" default="." /&gt;/etc/gitiles.config&lt;/Arg&gt;
&lt;/Call&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Logging with Logstash]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2012/10/logging-with-logstash/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-27T22:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2012/10/logging-with-logstash</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In these days I started looking up for an opensource, easy-to-use central logging system.
I read a lot of articles on the internet, and I found two good solution,
<a href="http://www.graylog2.org">Graylog2</a> and <a href="http://logstash.net/">LogStash</a>. Both system can
operate as syslog server and store our logs in database. I tried both system, and I
experienced both have small problems - but some of these problems are different.</p>

<h2>Graylog2</h2>

<p>Graylog has a very good-looking interface and a relative easy configuration file. It has
a lot of parameters, but the default configuraiton file is well-documented and easy to read.</p>

<p>Graylog uses a MongoDB for store some small stuffs and ElasticSearch for store and search logs.
The main advantage of this solution is the separated web interface. It can be installed anywhere,
it just need a some small configurations to connect to same ES/Mongo instances as Graylog server uses.</p>

<p>The web ui makes easy to search and filter logs, backlist some entries, and create a "channels" what is
a named filter setting, where you can follow what happening in a simple context.</p>

<p>But as I started use web interface and the server itself in everyday tasks, I found two problems:</p>

<ul>
<li>Web interface is does not make easy to write filters, because nor the interface, nor the documentation
not describe how filters will be matched against messages. Because these filters are simple regular
expressions, it is needed to know how to search some specific things. I sucked with it a lot of time
until I found a method to find something. It is need a lot of improvement.</li>
<li>Graylog seems does not take care about its input. After a week I found logging is stopped working. After
some investigation, I discovered the ElasticSearch eaten a lot of resources and generating a huge log.
After reading log I found the ElasticSearch is broken on some invalid characters in index files. I
tried to restart ES server and leave to recover itself for a hour but no luck, it stuck in recovering state.
Because I am not know well ES and graylog I started ask Google about these problems, but I did not find a
good solution for me. So I decided to move on from Graylog.</li>
</ul>


<h2>LogStash</h2>

<p>LogStash is a more robust logging solution. It is similar as syslog-ng but it does not restrict itself to working
as Syslog server (with other words: get infos from input like syslog server) but it can chew anything what is a text
stuff. It can use a lot of things as a log source, e.g.:</p>

<ul>
<li>Syslog server (it can act as syslog server, but see below)</li>
<li>Plain file</li>
<li>Raw TCP/UDP socket</li>
<li>Output of any executable</li>
<li>IRC/Jabber channels</li>
<li>Twitter</li>
<li>Stdin</li>
<li>Windows Eventlog</li>
<li>and so on...</li>
</ul>


<p>And it has a numerous output format too. What is important for me is it can use ElasticSearch and some No-SQL
databases as log-storing backend.</p>

<p>It has a built-in web interface for searching in log records, but <a href="https://github.com/rashidkpc/Kibana/">Kibana</a>
is a little better Web interface to search against ElasticSearch, it makes searching/filtering easier.</p>

<p>My current configuration is very easy:</p>

<ul>
<li>There is a central syslog server, provided by LogStash</li>
<li>All my server is logging here via RSyslog (default syslog server of Debian Linux)</li>
<li>LogStash is configured to store log messages in ElasticSearch after some parsing</li>
</ul>


<p>Basically, I followed the <a href="http://cookbook.logstash.net/recipes/syslog-pri/">official recipe</a> for this setup except
one thing: somehow I couldn't get working the date parser in the way what recipe says. So I tricked it out.</p>

<p>First, I created an Rsyslog config part, what I uploaded to /etc/rsyslog.d on every server:</p>

<p><code>text /etc/rsyslog.d/to-logstash.conf
$template LOGSTASH,"&lt;%PRI%&gt;%timegenerated:::date-rfc3164-buggyday% %HOSTNAME% %APP-NAME%: %msg:::drop-last-lf%\n"
$ActionForwardDefaultTemplate LOGSTASH
*.*   @1.2.3.4:514
</code></p>

<p>Note the <code>%timegenerated:::date-rfc3164-buggyday%</code> directive. The documentation of Rsyslog says it is basically
pads a day number with zero if it is smaller than 10. It is introduced to emulate a syslog-ng 'bug'.</p>

<p>After it I created a following configuration for logstash:</p>

<p>```text LogStash configuration
input {
  tcp {</p>

<pre><code>port =&gt; 514
type =&gt; syslog
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  udp {</p>

<pre><code>port =&gt; 514
type =&gt; syslog
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>filter {
  grok {</p>

<pre><code>  type =&gt; "syslog"
  pattern =&gt; [ "&lt;%{POSINT:syslog_pri}&gt;%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp} %{SYSLOGHOST:syslog_hostname} %{PROG:syslog_program}(?:\[%{POSINT:syslog_pid}\])?: %{GREEDYDATA:syslog_message}" ]
  add_field =&gt; [ "received_at", "%{@timestamp}" ]
  add_field =&gt; [ "received_from", "%{@source_host}" ]
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  syslog_pri {</p>

<pre><code>  type =&gt; "syslog"
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  date {</p>

<pre><code>  type =&gt; "syslog"
</code></pre>

<p>  #    syslog_timestamp => [ "MMM  d HH:mm:ss", "MMM dd HH:mm:ss" ]</p>

<pre><code>  syslog_timestamp =&gt; [ "MMM dd HH:mm:ss" ]
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  mutate {</p>

<pre><code>  type =&gt; "syslog"
  exclude_tags =&gt; "_grokparsefailure"
  replace =&gt; [ "@source_host", "%{syslog_hostname}" ]
  replace =&gt; [ "@message", "%{syslog_message}" ]
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  mutate {</p>

<pre><code>  type =&gt; "syslog"
  remove =&gt; [ "syslog_hostname", "syslog_message", "syslog_timestamp" ]
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}</p>

<p>output {
  elasticsearch {</p>

<pre><code>index =&gt; "syslog-%{+YYYY.MM.dd}"
embedded =&gt; false
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  #stdout { debug => true debug_format => json }
}</p>

<h1>vim: ts=2 sw=2 et</h1>

<p>```</p>

<p>Note the commented out date mapping. This is what original recipe says but I always got an exception
related to parser and DateFormat what complaining about invalid data in the date. With buggyday hack
on Rsyslog side I made dates 2-digit long, so it will always be parsed, I hope. It will reveals at least
Nov 1.</p>

<p>The last output stuff is just for debugging, it displays the parsed object in JSON format, this is a way
how can you check your all filter working correctly.</p>

<p>I sucked with parsing the message because my old rsyslog template has a typo and I could not imagine, what
failing.
After some digging, I found jls-grok RubyGem is contains a same parser what LogStash uses, so you can
check your filters via IRB. Just make sure you using 1.9.3 ruby, because Ruby 1.8 throws a SyntaxError
when you try <code>require 'grok-pure'</code> (what is recommended, because the simple 'grok' is searching a C lib).</p>

<p>```ruby Simple example for testing Grok filter
require 'rubygems'
require 'grok-pure'</p>

<p>grok = Grok.new</p>

<h1>I extracted patterns dir from jar package</h1>

<p>Dir.glob('patterns/*').each { |f| grok.add_patterns_from_file f }
s="Oct 27 19:01:09"
pattern = '%{SYSLOGTIMESTAMP:syslog_timestamp}'
grok.compile(pattern)
p grok.match(s).match.to_a # => ["Oct 27 19:01:09", "Oct 27 19:01:09", "Oct", "27", "19:01:09", "19", "01", "09"]
```</p>

<p>You can use exactly same pattern as you use in LogStash configuration file.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> If you see a <code>_grokparsefailure</code> tag in your tag list, then you do something wrong. This means
the filter what you using in first filter does not match correctly on your syslog message from Rsyslog.
The good news is LogStash stop evaluating filters on the first failing in debug mode, and leave @message
untouched (if you see the second mutate from end, you can see we replace @message with the content of
syslog_message, and remove unneccessary fields in the last mutate filter). If somehow it falls through
the grok filter and removes the original (raw) message, then simply comment out the last two filter by
prefixing lines with a hashmark.</p>

<p>As you see in the config  use an external ES server, not the embedded one, because I currently have a
working and configured ES instance, and I would like to use that. No other reason to not use embedded
ES server: if you currently not have an ES instance, then simply use what shipped with LogStash.</p>

<p>The embedded web interface of LogStash is a bit tricky thing, because I could not start as documentation says
via the java command, I had to extract the jar file and run standalone to check its user interface.
Don't expect something cool: It is just a textfield with a button and contains a link with a basic
query string what filters messages generated today.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I think Graylog is a great logging solution, but it needs some love for prevent crashing ES server with
invalid characters in the stored data. But the web interface and easy configuration makes it very,
really very lovely.</p>

<p>LogStash is a good solution if you want to handle multiple log sources or you want to validate/manipulate
your log messages or you want to distribute logs to multiple destinations. I think LogStash is a little
overkill if you just want a central syslog server, however - this is working as expected. So I took my
two cent on LogStash and not on Graylog - even if I would like to prefer Graylog.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
