<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: windows-8 | Hron's blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://hron.me/blog/tags/windows-8/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hron.me/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-18T00:58:49+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://hron.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[G치bor Garami]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rename Windows 8 Profile dir]]></title>
    <link href="http://hron.me/blog/2013/04/rename-windows-8-profile-dir/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T00:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://hron.me/blog/2013/04/rename-windows-8-profile-dir</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I ran into a weird situation: when I installed Windows, I used Live account to create my user.
In preview version of Windows 8 it created a profile dir based on the user part of e-mail address
of the Live account, so from hrgy@live.com it created an user hrgy with same profile dir. However,
the final version is changed it to create account based on your first name, it was "G치bor" in this
case. Notice the accented second letter.</p>

<p>The problem with folders containing non-ASCII char in its name is obvious: not all program can handle
it correctly. It has a displaying problems in some apps, and some apps cannot create their files in
this profile.</p>

<p>The fix was not so easy but I now describe required steps.</p>

<p>First if you do not have an another administrator user than you, then you have to create it. Windows 8
does not allow to log into the built-in Administrator account anymore, so you have to create one in
Control Panel. It's pretty straighforward and net contains a bunch of howtos for it, so I skip describing
this step.</p>

<p>Now, log out from your account, and log in into the new one.</p>

<p>Start <code>regedit</code> and navigate to <code>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\Windows NT\CurrentVersion\ProfileList</code></p>

<p>In the subkeys (subfolders) find one what displays your old dirname in <code>ProfileImagePath</code> attribute. In my
case the value was <code>C:\Users\G치bor</code>. Right click, edit and replace last part of the path to what you want to use.</p>

<p><strong>Important:</strong> Even if world collapsing, <strong>do not log in into your own account (what being modified)</strong>
until you finish these steps!</p>

<p>Then, you have to reboot into Safe mode. The easiest way is press <code>Shift + F8</code> during boot. If you
seeing the Windows splash displaying in "wrong" resolution then you are in Safe mode.</p>

<p><strong>Important:</strong> you have to log in into the newly created admin account, <em>not</em> into your own one!</p>

<p>Then you have to rename your profile folder. Start a command prompt in Safe mode, and type following:</p>

<pre><code>cd C:\Users
move old_name new_name
</code></pre>

<p>The <code>old_name</code> is the old name of your profile directory, the <code>new_name</code> is what you specified in RegEdit. In
my case it was:</p>

<pre><code>cd C:\Users
move G치bor hron
</code></pre>

<p>Now you are done! If you striclty follwed this tutorial, then if you reboot and log in into your account, you do not see
any change, except the %USERPROFILE% environment variable carries the new name.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> I saw only one bug: iCloud Photo stream stored the full path of my Pictures folder in its database and I had to relocate it.
It's a bug in iCloud, not a Windows problem.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: This tutorial is tested by me but I do not guarantee anything. Take a backup from your important data before start doing
this. I am not responsible if your data lose, you cannot login anymore or your kitten vanishes.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
